<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A golden keye opening the locke to eternall happines. Containing seuen most sweete and comfortable directions to a Christian life. By Francis Dillingham, Bachelor in Diuinitie, and Preacher of Gods word at Wilden in Bedfordshire. The contents follow in the next page.</title>
            <author>Dillingham, Francis, d. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12431</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853894</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176639</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264220861</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 6886</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S118687</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99853894e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176639)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 579:08, 579:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A golden keye opening the locke to eternall happines. Containing seuen most sweete and comfortable directions to a Christian life. By Francis Dillingham, Bachelor in Diuinitie, and Preacher of Gods word at Wilden in Bedfordshire. The contents follow in the next page.</title>
                  <author>Dillingham, Francis, d. 1625.</author>
                  <author>Dillingham, Francis, d. 1625. Christian oeconomy. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52, [2] p.; [4], 57; [5], 34 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Windet] for Iohn Tapp, and are to be sold at his shop on Tower-hil neare the Bulwarke Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In two parts; register and pagination separate.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 has separate dated title page, reading: Christian Oeconomy. Or Houshold gouernment.</note>
                  <note>"A sermon preached at the solemnization of the funeral of the right vertuous and worshipful Lady Elizabeth Luke" has separate dated title page.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 formerly also STC 6880; identified as STC 6880 on UMI microfilm, reel 579.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 579 #8 (part 1 only) and #9 (part 2 only, identified as STC 6880) (Folger Shakespeare Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Luke, Elizabeth, --  Lady --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176639:1"/>
            <p>A GOLDEN KEYE, OPENING THE LOCKE TO ETER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NALL HAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PINES.</p>
            <p>Containing seuen most sweete and comfortable directions to a Christian life.</p>
            <p>By FRANCIS DILLINGHAM, <hi>Bachelor in Diuinitie, and Preacher of Gods word at</hi> WILDEN <hi>in Bedfordshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Contents follow in the next Page.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for IOHN TAPP, and are to be sold at his Shop on To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer-hil neare the Bulwarke Gate. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:176639:2"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 The Fierie triall.</item>
               <item>2 The yong mans scripture.</item>
               <item>3 The difficultie of saluation. Oeconomie or houshould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment shewing the duties of</item>
               <item>4 Husbands and wiues.</item>
               <item>5 Parents and children.</item>
               <item>6 Maisters and seruants.</item>
               <item>7 A funerall sermon.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176639:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT vertuous, wise, and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Lady, the Lady</hi> Mary Winfeild, <hi>Grace</hi> and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree things there are (right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady) which as in all times, haue hindered the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, so in these our daies, do not a little keepe men from sincere pietie: worldlines plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:3"/>and persecution. Touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the two first, in the <hi>14.</hi> of <hi>Luke</hi> the <hi>18.</hi> verse, they which were bidden to the Lordes supper, excused them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues after this manner: One said, I haue bought a farme, and another said, I haue married a wife, and therefore I cannot come. The world is like vnto a Sea, in which many men are drowned. The fish Polypus, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise a sottish creature, yet in the catching of shel-fish, vseth strange diligence: euen so some haue wisedome, onely for gain; but as concerning religion, they are merely brutish. As for
<pb facs="tcp:176639:3"/>pleasure, if it be a principle that <hi>plures gula quam gladio periere:</hi> moe haue perished by gluttony then by the sword: How many haue perished tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row voluptuousnes? Riches and pleasures are many a mans God. Now concerning persecution, how many are so effeminate that they cannot abide any tryall? Fiery tryal through the mercies of God, wee haue none by the meanes of a gratious King, whom the Lord blesse continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; yet are the godly afflicted with vices and sinnes: blessed are they that can mourne for
<pb facs="tcp:176639:4"/>the sinnes of other men: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the godly persecuted with the sinnes of men only, but also with their tongues. He that feareth God now a daies, is made a wonder amongst men. This is a grieuous persecution, because it is done by men, that professe the same religion; and sogrieuous is it to many, that for this cause they will not bee counted religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: they had rather bee open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophane, then publiquely religious, lest they should be scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at. Shall wee thinke that these men would abide the fiery tryall, that cannot abide this so easie a kind of tryall? Now that
<pb facs="tcp:176639:4"/>men may relinquish the world and worldly pleasures, and also that they bee not offended with persecution, I haue penned this treatise: the Lorde blesse the same, to all that shall read it. A true Christian may say with the Poet:
<q>
                  <l>Quocūque aspicio nihil est nisi p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>̄tus &amp; aether</l>
                  <l>Fluctibus hic tumidus, nubibus ille minax.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whethersoeuer I cast my eies, there is nothing but the sea, and the aire, the one raging with his waues, the other threatning with clouds. To conclude, as I thoght good to publish this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, so I iudged it meete to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the same to your worshippe,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:5"/>being a true paterne of piety, and a rare example of religion. The Lord for his mercies sake, multiply these his graces vpon you, that you may liue Eternally.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worshippes<lb/> to command,<lb/> FRANCIS DILLINGHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176639:5"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE FIERY TRIAL.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1. PETER 4.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Dearely beloued, thinke it not strange concerning the fiery tryall, which thing is to try you, as though some strange thing happened vnto you.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T this 12. verse S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Peter</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Iewes to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer afflictions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the fiery af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: In which exhortation these things are plainly layd down: First, a friendly compellation, in these
<pb facs="tcp:176639:6"/>words; <hi>Dearely beloued:</hi> Secondly, a remouing of a wrong and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous conceit, touching the fiery affliction, in these words; <hi>Thinke it not strange concerning the fiery try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as though some strange thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto you:</hi> Thirdly, a reason to suffer the fiery affliction, in these wordes; <hi>Which is to trie you.</hi> And it is thus to bee framed: that which tryeth men, as the fire tryeth the gold, is to be suffered; but the fiery affliction tryeth men as the fire trieth the gold, therefore it is to be suffered.</p>
               <p>Touching the friendly compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: Saint <hi>Peter</hi> vseth it to make his exhortation of greater force, that it may take place with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, for men will receiue vsually the exhortations, admonitions, and reproofes of those which loue them; as contrary, they will reiect
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176639:6"/>and despise the reproofe of them that hate them.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <hi>Tres sunt causae</hi> (saith <hi>Aristotle) quibus efficitur vt ei qui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, &amp;c.</hi> There are three things that procure of a mans Auditors cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, wisedome, honesty, and loue, wheresoeuer these things are to be found, there the hearers reape be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite and profite; but where they are not, they goe away without a blessing. Hence we learne the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere loue that should bee betwixt Christians, seeing <hi>Peter</hi> calleth the Christians dearely beloued. Vnto this duety Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his first E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle, 3. chap. 18. ver. exhorteth vs, saying: <hi>My little children, let vs not loue in word and in tongue, or speech, but in worke and truth.</hi> There are many arguments to perswade Christians to loue one another: First, afflictions; Christians suffer the same afflictions, therefore they
<pb facs="tcp:176639:7"/>ought to loue another. <hi>Natura as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert,</hi> saith the Orator, <hi>Pro Muraena, vt cis faueamus &amp;c.</hi> Very nature doth teach vs to fauor those, which suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the same dangers, out of the which we are deliuered. Seeing then Christians suffer the same afflictions in name, in goods, in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and euery way, let them loue one another, otherwise they sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the very light of nature: Secondly, Christians are renued to the image of God, and so haue the same similitude and likenesse. Now all men know, that loue ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of likenesse and similitude. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudo morum parit amicitiam:</hi> the likenes of manners begetteth friendship. What a strange thing is it then, that men will not loue those that are Christians, which are renued into the same image with themselues: doth it not plainly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176639:7"/>that they haue not the image of God renued in truth, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in appearance? Wee know, saith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. Epistle 3. chapt. 14. ver. that we are translated from death vnto life, because we loue the brethren. Hence it appeareth, that many are still in death because they hate Christians, as it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in all places: Thirdly, nature it selfe teacheth loue. <hi>Siccata tellus imbre rigari, &amp;c.</hi> The earth being drie, desireth to be watered: when the heauens are full of water, they desire to power it into the bosome of the earth; such natural sympathy is there betwixt these creatures. Doe not they then teach vs loue? Aske, saith <hi>Iob,</hi> chap. 12. ver. 7. the beastes, and they shall teach thee, and the fowles of the heauen, and they shall tell thee, or speake to the earth, and it shall shew thee,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:8"/>or the fishes of the Sea, and they shall declare vnto thee. So say I, the very insensible creatures teach vs loue: Fourthly, men are made of the same matter; yea, they breath the same aire, and yet no loue haue they one to another. It is a true saying that, <hi>Fratrum irae inter se inimicissimae</hi> the anger of brethren is the greatest anger that can be, so the hatred of Christian brethren is the greatest hatred that can be. <hi>A brother offended,</hi> saieth <hi>Salomon,</hi> Prouerbes 18. chap. ver. 19. <hi>is harder to winne then a strong Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and their contentions are like the barre of a Palace. Vt aqua ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactacum ad frigiditatem, &amp;c.</hi> As water that hath beene hotte, being cold againe, is colder then it was by nature: so loue being turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hatred, there ariseth the greatest hatred. <hi>Vt adamas sifrangi contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176639:8"/>&amp;c.</hi> As the Adamant, if it be once broken, is shiuered into so smal pieces that they can hardly be seene; so the nearest friendshippe, if it be dissolued, is turned into the greatest hatred. This doctrine of loue, as it hath beene alwaies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, so especially in these times: for as our Sauior Christ saith, Mat. chap. 24. ver. 12. <hi>Because iniquity shal encrease, the loue of many shall bee cold.</hi> Excellently writeth <hi>Bernard</hi> 33. Sermon vpon the Canticles. <hi>Omnes amici et omnes inimici, &amp;c.</hi> All friends and all enemies, all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars and all aduersaries, all of a house and yet none at peace, all neighbours and yet all seeking their owne things. That our loue bee right Christian loue, let vs consider the kindes of loue: First, there is a naturall loue, as of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents towards their children, but
<pb facs="tcp:176639:9"/>Christians must not stay there. Secondly there is a ciuil loue, as one heathen man loueth another for ciuility, neither must a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an rest in this loue: Thirdly, there is a loue for commodity, which is the common loue of the world, and indeede this is nothing but selfe-loue. For <hi>si ob tuam causam cuiquam, &amp;c.</hi> If thou doest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite any for thy owne sake, it is no benefite but vsury: Fourthly, there is a loue for pleasure, which loue likewise is very common in the world: this is the loue of pot-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, of dicers and carders, which is soone dissolued. <hi>Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum ignis qui, &amp;c.</hi> As the fire that is kindled in light matter, is soone exringuished, so loue which ariseth of pleasure, is soone put out: Fiftly, there is a christian loue, which is, when we loue men in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176639:9"/>Lord, and for the Lord. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> Ephes. chap. 6. ver. 1. commandeth children to obey their parents in the Lorde: that is, so farre as they commaund that, which the Lord commandeth them; so wee must loue men in the Lord: If by reason of loue, they will vs to doe vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, we must rmember that it is better to obey God then men. Now we loue men for the Lord: first because he hath commanded vs so to doe: secondly, because of the graces of God which we see in them; and this is right christian loue, and they who cannot loue men, because they see the graces of God in them, plainely shew, that they haue not christian loue. What shall wee thinke then of those, who hate Christian men because they are Christians? As S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Iohn</hi> saith, surely they are not
<pb facs="tcp:176639:10"/>passed from death to life, and therefore are in a fearefull estate. And thus much touching the friendly compellation. Now I come to the remoouing of the wrong conceit of the fierie trial, which is the second part of this portion of Scripture. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing of this conceit is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, for the godly haue beene much troubled with the prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the wicked, and with their owne miseries and calamities. <hi>O Lord,</hi> saith <hi>Ieremy</hi> chap. 12. ver. 1. <hi>if I dispute with thee thou art righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, yet let me talke with thee of thy iudgements: wherefore doth the way of the wicked prosper, why are they in wealth that rebelliously trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse? Dauid</hi> in the 73. Psalme also saith, <hi>As for me, my feete were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most gone, my sleps had well nere slipt, for I fretted at the foolish, when I sawe
<pb facs="tcp:176639:10"/>the prosperity of the wicked.</hi> The Heathen man <hi>Diogenes</hi> in Tully, in his 3. Booke <hi>De natura Deorum,</hi> vttered this speech: <hi>Improborum prosperitates secundaeque res, &amp;c.</hi> The prosperity of the wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth all the power of God. <hi>Tully</hi> also himselfe in his Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pro Flac.</hi> sayth of Hierusalem <hi>quam chara dijs immortalibus. &amp;c.</hi> It is manifest how it was belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, in that it was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: thus the Heathen man iudged of Gods fauour, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and crosses. Yet further to shew the necessity of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueall of this conceit: if men should iudge by naturall reason, might they not thinke it strange, that a father should suffer his children to be murthered before his eyes, when hee is able to res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue them, and deliuer them? The
<pb facs="tcp:176639:11"/>godly are Gods children; and is it not strange, that he should suffer them to be burned before his eyes, when he is able to deliuer them? Strange it is to naturall reason, but strange it must not bee to those, which haue sauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: the reasons shall be set downe in handling of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles reason. Before I come to the handling of the same, Christian reader, meditate of as strange things in Diuinity, as the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods children: First, God hath concluded all men vnder sin. Rom. 11. <hi>Nostra est</hi> saith <hi>Bernard</hi> Ser. 1. <hi>De dominica prima post octa. Epi. Adami cu'pa, &amp;c.</hi> Adams fault is ours, for wee haue sinned, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in another, and the fault shall be imputed vnto vs, by Gods righteous, although secret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Secondly, God reiected
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176639:11"/>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> and chose <hi>Dauid:</hi> yea, hee chose some to saluation, and reiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed others. Excellently writeth <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> Serm. 20. <hi>De verbis Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoli tu homo, expecta, &amp;c.</hi> Thou, O man, lookest for an answere of me, and I my selfe am also a man; therefore both thou, and I, let vs hearken to him that saith: O man, who art thou that disputest with God? Better farre is faithfull ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance then rash knowledge: seeke for merite, thou shalt find but punishment. O depth! <hi>Peter</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the thiefe beleeueth. O depth! Thou seekest a reason of this, I will tremble at the deepenesse; thou reasonest, I will wonder: thou disputest, I will beleeue: A depth I see, to the bottome, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth them vnsearchable waies of God, and thou wilt search them. Whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:176639:12"/>liketh not this answere, let him seeke for better learned; but let him take heede hee find not presumers. Thirdly, God hardneth whom he will: Fourthly, he puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth those that go about a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worke, Iudges 20. Fiftly, he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth not all that commit the same sinne, Exo. 32. <hi>Fatum aspici non inspici vult, &amp;c.</hi> Gods secrets must bee looked vpon, but they must not be looked into: belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued they must be without curious knowledge. It is sufficient to know that they are, <hi>Vt papisiones &amp; minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta quaedam, &amp;c.</hi> As Butterflies and small creatures flie about the light of a Candle, vntil they be burnt; so mans minde itcheth to know se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets: it will needs touch heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fire vntill it vanish away, and climbe vp into the tower of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, vntill it fall downe.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:176639:12"/>
               <p> Thus I haue shewed thee as strange things in Diuinity, as the afflictions of Gods owne deare seruants. Now I come to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the fiery tryall: The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why God doeth suffer his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to passe thorow the fire, is to try them: as gold is tryed in the fire, so Gods true seruants are try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from counterfeit seruants, by the fiery tryall of afflictions; and no doubt if GOD should send the fiery tryall, many vnsound professors would manifest them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. <hi>Constantius</hi> meaning and intending to proue some Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that were in his Palace, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were good and sound men or no, called them all forth, and said: if they would worshippe his Gods, they should remaine still with him; but if they would not, they must depart, with thankesgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:13"/>for that they were not puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed; but indeed he expelled those that left the true God, and fell to a false worshippe; affirming, that they would neuer be good subiects that were traytors to God. Thus we see how trials discerne betwixt good and euill; betwixt <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Demas;</hi> betwixt <hi>Cephas</hi> and <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas;</hi> betwixt <hi>Simon Peter</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus.</hi> Let not vs then thinke the fiery tryall a strange thing, seeing by it true Christians are discerned from false Christians; as drosse is tryed from the golde by the fire. Now as the Lord hath this end in sending the fierie tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; so likewise hath he many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the encrease of his Church: for Martyrdome doth encrease the same <hi>Sanguis martyrum est semen ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clesiae.</hi> The blood of Martyrs is the seed of the Church. <hi>Quoties metun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176639:13"/>Christiani toties multiplicantur.</hi> As often as Christians are cutte downe, so often are they multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The children of Israel, Exod. 1.12. the more they were vexed, the more they encreased. By Martyrdome was <hi>Iustine Martyr</hi> conuerted. <hi>Euseb.</hi> in his 4. booke and 8. chapter citeth <hi>Iustine</hi> his words, touching himselfe, in this forme: <hi>Nam ipse ego cum Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonis dogmatibus, &amp;c.</hi> I my selfe being a Platonist, hearing that Christians were traduced, and yet neuer daunted with death, or any fearefull punishment; thought it could not be, that this kind of men should be subiect to malice, or to the desire of vaine pleasure. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> in his 22. booke <hi>De ciuitate Dei</hi> and 8. chapter writeth thus of Christians; <hi>Ligabantur, vreban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, includebantur, caedebantur, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicabantur.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176639:14"/>They were bound, they were burnt, they were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned, they were beaten, yet were they multiplyed. The murtherers of Martyrs, are like to those that cutte downe trees, many moe branches spring out of the rootes, then there were boughes before: so out of the ashes of Martyres arise moe Christians then were before. Thus we see a second reason and cause, why God doeth suffer his Church to passe thorow the fiery tryall: namely, the multiplication of the same. <hi>Iulius Palmer,</hi> as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Foxe</hi> reporteth, was conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the suffering of Martyrs, in the bloody persecution that was in this land. And thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the second cause of the fiery tryall. The third cause of Gods fiery tryall, is to giue his seruants so suffering, a greater weight of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176639:14"/>glory: for the momentany light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, saith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Cor. chap. 4. of our tribulation, worketh an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding weight of glory in vs; for although good workes, as wee shall heare, deserue not, yet doeth God of his mercy plentifully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them. Mat. 5. <hi>Happy are they which suffer persecution, for theirs is the kingdome of heauen: happy are you when men speake euill of you, and persecute you:</hi> and againe, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and be glad, for that your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is great in heauen. Nemo,</hi> saieth <hi>Chrysostome, homilia</hi> 2. <hi>in Epist. ad Colos. talem vitae, &amp;c.</hi> No man sheweth such conuersation of life, that he can be worthy of Gods kingdome, but is wholly the gift of God: wherefore hee saith, when ye haue done all things, say ye, we are vnprofitable seruants, for we haue done but the things wee ought.
<pb facs="tcp:176639:15"/>Excellently writeth <hi>Ambrose,</hi> in <hi>Exhor. ad Virg. Vnde mihi tantum meriti, &amp;c.</hi> Whence haue I such merite, seeing mercy is my crown? What shal we say then of Papists, who make the suffering of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs so meritorious, that they make vp the treasure of the Church? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this vile and detestable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, let vs remember, that <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth thus in the 143. Psalme: <hi>Enter not into iudgement with thy seruant, O Lord, for no flesh is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in thy sight;</hi> and againe in the 130. hee saith, <hi>If thou, O Lorde, dost mark what is done amisse, who is able to stand? Daniel</hi> also in his 9. chap. and 18. verse, prayeth thus: <hi>We doe not present our supplications before thee for our owne righteousnes, but for thy great tender mercies. Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis,</hi> sayth Pope <hi>Leo</hi> 83. <hi>Epist. mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum sanctorum in conspectu, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176639:15"/>Although the death of many Saints bee pretious in the sight of the Lord, yet was not the death of any Saint a propitiation for the sinnes of the world. The iust haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their crownes, and not giuen a crowne; and the faithful by their fortitude are become examples of patience, not gifts of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Yet further to giue reasons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this vngodly doctrine: The satisfaction of Christ is of infinite value, therefore there neede no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioining of the satisfactions of Saints: to this argument <hi>Bellarmine</hi> answereth; it is meete that the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Saints bee not in vaine: as though the passions of saints were in vaine, except they were adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the passions of Christ, to make vp the treasure of the Church. Hath not their owne Pope set downe the vse of them in
<pb facs="tcp:176639:16"/>the wordes which I recited? Yea, are there not many other vses be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the making vp of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the Church: Secondly, the Saints haue receiued a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; there wanteth therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their labours, which may be bestowed vpon other men, to satisfie for their sinnes: to this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, the same answere is sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in effect, wherefore I passe it ouer: Thirdly, if Saints could satisfie for our sinnes, then were they our redeemers and sauiours; but onely Christ is our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. To this Argument hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth, that they are our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, which is blasphemy; for they are redeemed with the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of Christ, and neuer are they called redeemers in the whole Scripture. <hi>The blood of Iesus Christ,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. chap. <hi>purgeth vs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176639:16"/>from all sinne,</hi> and in the 7. of the Reu. 17. ver. <hi>They which are come out of the great tribulation, are said to haue washed their robes in the blood of the Lamb,</hi> which Lamb is Christ Iesus. Now here a question by the way may be demanded: Did all the Saints goe to heauen immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as wel as Martyrs? I answere, <hi>Augustine</hi> in his 20. booke, <hi>De ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei</hi> and 9. chapt. writeth thus: for although they are not yet with their bodies, yet their soules doe euen now reigne with him, but of a part, we vnderstand the whole, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the rest, which pertaine to the Church; which is the kingdome of God: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the rest of the soules are not tormented in purgatory, while the Martyrs raigne in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with Christ. <hi>Omnis anima Deo chara,</hi> saith <hi>Nazianzen</hi> in his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration concerning <hi>Caesarius, Post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam
<pb facs="tcp:176639:17"/>corporis vinculis, &amp;c.</hi> Euery soule beloued of God, being loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed out of the body, flyeth ioyfully vnto the Lord, and enioyeth the happinesse that is layd vp for the same. Hence two maine points of Popery are throwen down: First, Purgatory: Secondly, praier for the dead; <hi>Iniuriam facit Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyri,</hi> saith <hi>Augustine, qui orat pro Martyre.</hi> Hee doeth iniury to a Martyre, that prayeth for a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre; so he doth iniury to a Saint, that prayeth for a Saint, supposing him to be in misery. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching purgatory; <hi>Iustine</hi> in his 60. question writeth thus: <hi>Est de Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite &amp; Lazaro narratio euidens, &amp;c.</hi> The history of the rich man and Lazarus is an euident narration, and a manifest representation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this doctrine: that after the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the soule from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176639:17"/>men neither by prouidence, neither by labour can get or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any helpe. Fourthly, the Lord doth send the fiery tryall vnto his seruants, that they may be made like vnto Christ; which is, a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular vse of the fiery triall: if wee will raigne with Christ, we must also suffer with Christ: Christ was put to death, and that we may be conformable to Christ our head, wee that are his members must looke for the same death. <hi>Neque,</hi> saith <hi>Cyprian, nobis est ignominia pati &amp;c.</hi> Neither is it a shame for vs to suffer of our brethren, that which Christ hath suffered: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a glory for them to doe that which <hi>Iudas</hi> did. Againe, saith the same worthy Martyre: <hi>Filius Dei passus est, &amp;c.</hi> The sonne of God suffered to make vs the sonnes of God, and shall not men suffer that
<pb facs="tcp:176639:18"/>they may continue the sonnes of God? Wherefore remember this fourth end, why God doeth lay vpon his seruants the fiery tryall; which indeede should moue all Christians to endure the same, if there were nothing els in the fiery tryall. Fiftly, the Lord doth send the fiery tryall to exercise the graces that he hath bestowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs: for in the fiery tryall is exercised our faith, whereby wee beleeue the promise of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith is defined in the 11. of the Heb. to be a ground of things that are hoped for, and an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things that are not seene. Secondly, hope is exercised, which waiteth for the reward that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued; and these are two graces of God, that stay euery Christian man in temptation: faith appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the promise, and hope
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176639:18"/>looking for the reward promised. If humane hope, cōforteth &amp; streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thneth men in their miseries; how much more shold a christian hope strengthen Christians? <hi>Spes facit vt videat cū terras vndi{que} nullas, naufra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus in medijs brachia iactet aquis,</hi> hope maketh him that hath suffered shipwracke, when hee can see no land, to cast and spread his armes in the middest of the waters. Againe, <hi>spes etiam valida solatur compede venctum, crura sonant ferro sed canit inter opus.</hi> Hope comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the prisoner, his legges make a noise with chaines, yet is he mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie at his worke: Other ends of the fiery triall, might I haue recited but I desire breuitie, I come to the vses of this doctrine: First if men must not thinke the fierie triall a strange thing, what shall we thinke of those that will bee Christians,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:19"/>and yet cannot abide small trialls; as the losse of name, of goods, and health for Christ his sake: Let vs remember that which <hi>Cyprian</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: <hi>Nec Christiani vltra durare, aut esse possumus si ad hoc ventum est, vt proditorum minas &amp; insidias per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timescamus:</hi> Neither can wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue or be Christians any longer, if it be come to this, that we feare the threatning and deceiptes of wicked men. The second vse of the doctrine, is to shew that all things worke together to the good of Gods children: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. ver. <hi>For doth not the Fierie triall helpe them sooner to Heauen;</hi> which is the place that they long for: yea heere wee may see, how he order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the sins of tyrants to his owne glorie: They that doe afflict and vexe Gods Church, do sinne most grieuously; yet this affliction God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176639:19"/>willeth, as <hi>Peter</hi> saith: 1. Epist. 4. cap. 19. ver. <hi>they which be afflicted by the will of God, let them commit their soules to him in well dooing as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a faithfull Creator.</hi> Excellently wtiteth <hi>Fulgentius libr.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Moni: Deus itaque licet author &amp;c.</hi> That is, God therefore although hee bee not the author of euill thoughts, yet is hee an orderer of euill wills, and by the bad worke of euery wicked one, he ceaseth not to effect that which is good. To <hi>Fulgentius</hi> agreeth <hi>Augustine</hi> in his booke, <hi>De gen. ad literam: Vitiorum non est author deus, sed est ordinator.</hi> God is not the Author of our sinnes, yet is hee the disposer of them. The third vse of the doctrine is to shew the truth of Religion in that men will die rather then they will forsake their Religion, is it not a thing aboue Nature, that men
<pb facs="tcp:176639:20"/>should rather loose their liues then forsake their beleefe in God. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable is the speech of <hi>Ignatius, Frumentum ego dei sum, bestiarum dentibus molor &amp; subigor, vt panis mundus efficiar Christo:</hi> I am the Lord his corne, I care not to bee ground with the teeth of beastes, so be it I bee made fine bread for Christ: But some will say, haue not Heretiques their Martyrs; yes, but mark the difference in three things. First in the cause, <hi>Non paena sed cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa facit Martyrem,</hi> not the punnish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but the cause maketh a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre. Secondly, marke the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of true Martyrs. Thirdly, marke the multitude. The Diuell hath his Martyrs. As he hath his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and his Sacraments: so hath hee also his Martyrs, for he doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze their sences, so that they feele not the grieuousnesse of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176639:20"/>punnishment which they suffer. To conclude this text of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if thou feelest thy frailtie and doubtest that thou canst not abide the fierie triall; Remember this saying of Cyprian <hi>Deus adiuuat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micantes, vincentes coronat, retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione pietatis paternae remunerans in nobis quidquid ipse praestitit &amp; honorans quod ipse perfecit.</hi> God doth helpe those that striue, hee crowneth those that ouercome, rewarding in vs whatsoeuer hee hath wrought, and honouring whatsoeuer he hath perfected: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine remember what <hi>Ambrose</hi> writeth in his first booke of offices 38. Chap. <hi>Gratia praeparandus est a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus, exercenda mens, stabilienda ad constantiam, vt nullis perturbari ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus possit terroribus, nullis frangi molestiis, nullis suppliciis cedere.</hi> The mind is to be prepared with grace,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:21"/>and to bee established vnto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie, that it may not bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with any terrours, nor dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed with any sorrowes, nor yeelde with any punishment. The Lord of his infinite goodnes make vs to suffer with Christ, that we may raigne with Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:176639:21"/>
               <head>THE YOVNG MANS Scripture.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ECCLES. Chap. 11. verse 9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Reioice O yong man in thy youth and let thine hart cheere thee, and walke in the waies of thine hart and in the sight of thine eyes: but know that for all these things God will bring thee to iudgement.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His portion of holy writ may be called the Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister hath his
<pb facs="tcp:176639:22"/>scripture. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. chap. 2. ver. He must be apt to teach. <hi>St sacerdos est</hi> saith <hi>Hierom</hi> vpon the 2. of <hi>Haggey Sciat legem dei: si ignoratlegem, ipse se arguit non esse sacerdotem domini:</hi> If a man be a minister, let him know the lawe of God, if hee knoweth not the lawe, he proueth himselfe not to be the Lords Minister; Yea the learned father <hi>Augustine</hi> in his fourth booke, <hi>De doctrina Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> 16. chap. writeth thus, <hi>Tres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicas Epistolas ad Titum, &amp; ad Timotheum, ante oculos habere debet, cui est in Ecclesia doctoris persona im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posita.</hi> Hee ought to haue before his eies the three Epistles of <hi>Paule</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> who doth susteine the person of a teacher in the Church. The Magistrate also hath his Scripture 82. Psalme: <hi>I said yee are Gods but yee shall die like men:</hi> The rich man hath his scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176639:22"/>1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. chap. 17. ver. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they bee not high minded, and that they trust not in vncertaine riches, but in the liuing God: that they doe good and be rich in good workes and ready to distribute and communicate.</hi> The poore man hath his scripture, <hi>Pro</hi> 30.9. verse: <hi>Giue mee not pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, least I be poore and steale, and take the name of God in vaine.</hi> The olde man hath his scripture <hi>Esay</hi> 65.20. <hi>There shall bee no more there a child of yeares, nor an olde man that hath not filled his daies, for hee that shall be an hundred yeares old, shall die as a yong man, but the sinner bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an hundred yeare old shalbe accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</hi> Lastly, the yong man hath his Scripture euen the text now read vnto you: In which these two things are to be considered. The first is a taunting cōcession in these words;
<pb facs="tcp:176639:23"/>
                  <hi>Reioice O yong man, &amp;c.</hi> Or an Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie which is, when by pronuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee signifie a diuerse thing, from that which the wordes doe sound. The second thing is a bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or restraint for the yongman in these words; <hi>but know that God will bring thee to iudgement for all these things:</hi> Touching the Irony or mocking of the yong man, it may bee questioned how it can be lawfull. I answere, when it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to instruction, and not to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and deceiue men, then it is good and lawfull and may bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. Examples whereof we haue in God himselfe in <hi>Elias,</hi> mocking the Priests of <hi>Baall,</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle <hi>Paul</hi> who when hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the follie of such as did boast of such things as they had not, hee did greatly abase himselfe and aduance the Corinthians, by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176639:23"/>such a kinde of speaking: Now to the meaning of the words touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worde <hi>Reioice;</hi> wee must not vnderstand onely that which the Philosophers call ioy or reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; which is the mirth of the minde, and commeth not to the outward parts, but also outward mirth, and all kinde of vnlawfull pleasures: Yea the abuse of lawfull pleasures, and touching the worde <hi>Young man:</hi> wee must not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand him onely that is of the age betwixt thirtie yeares and fortie yeares, as the Philosophers take the young man; who diuiding age into infancie, childhood and strip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, youth and olde age make young age begin at thirtie yeeres and to reach to fortie: but we must further stretch the signification of this worde; <hi>Solomon</hi> also diuideth not onely the Young man, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb facs="tcp:176639:24"/>the old man that followeth his pleasures: but he nameth the yong man, because by reason of yeeres, hee is especiallie giuen to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures. Furthermore <hi>Solomon</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the hart, &amp; saith, let thy heart cheere thee and the eies also, and walke in the waies of thine eies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause as the <hi>Rabbins</hi> say, these two members are the brokers of sinne, the hart lusteth or desireth, and the eie seeth. That which the eie seeth, the heart desireth, therefore <hi>Iob</hi> saith, <hi>I made a Couenant with mine eies, why then should I lo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke on a maide;</hi> And thus much touching the meaning of the Irony. As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the meaning of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint of the Young man, it nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not any explication: Now to the doctrine. Hence wee learne, that young men are wonderfully addicted to their pleasures, so are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176639:24"/>many olde men also, but young men especiallie; therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> derideth them, because they are so addicted vnto them, <hi>Wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> saith the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> 119. Psalme, 9. verse. <hi>Shall a young man redresse his way?</hi> because youth is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen most to licentiousnes: he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monisheth thē to frame their liues betime to Gods worde; A young man is set as it were in a place where two waies meete, and vnto him come two tempters: the one vertue, the other vice and pleasure, as there did to <hi>Hercules:</hi> Vertue commeth with chaste eies and modest attire: Pleasure commeth with wanton lookes, with a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted countenance, and with who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish attire: Vertue saith, if thou wilt attaine to felicitie, and if thou wilt bee happie, thou must take paines; but pleasure saith, if thou
<pb facs="tcp:176639:25"/>wilt follow mee, I will shew thee a pleasant life, thou shalt care for nothing, but for fine meates and drinke: but how thou maiest lie easily and play continuallie, thus the young man is tempted: Vertue propoundeth vnto him labour, if hee will be happie: Vice propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto him pleasure, a cleane contrarie way. Now the young mans nature being prone and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to leaue labour and to follow pleasure embraceth the same. Hence it is plaine, that pleasure fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the young mans nature; and indeede what doth hee thinke of; what doth hee speake; of what doth hee dreame; what doth he follow: pleasure, nothing but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; hard it is for a man to resist anger, but harder it is to resist plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; pleasure is ingrafted and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished vp with men. Secondly, it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176639:25"/>is continuall, anger is but short: Thirdly, anger is bitter, pleasure is sweet: Fourthly pleasure is spred through the whole bodie: Fiftly, pleasure is fraudulent and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Seeing then the case stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth so, that pleasure is diffused through all the parts of man, and is naturall vnto him, needes must hee follow the same, as the fish then is taken with the baite, so are young men taken with pleasure: Wherefore let mee speake to thee that art a young man, deale with pleasure, as if thou wouldest deale with a dogge, if thou desirest to be rid of him, thou driuest him away; for if thou doest feede him he will abide with thee: so if thou desirest to be rid of pleasures, chastise them that they may fly away, if thou dost foster them they will remaine still. Againe; <hi>Si vis in perpetua voluptate
<pb facs="tcp:176639:26"/>manere, non voluptatibus adiicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum sed cupiditatibus detrahendum:</hi> If thou wilt liue in perpetual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, adde not to thy pleasures, but take from thy desires. Now let vs see the particular pleasures that men are giuen vnto, to omitt the pleasure of smelling; for although pleasure doth increase by smelling garments, yet I will omit to speake of this pleasure. To omit then the pleasure of smelling, and to come to the pleasure of tasting, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men are ouercome with glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie and drunkennes, so that they make themselues the diuels swine; but I haue spoken and written of these sinnes, wherefore I passe them ouer. Secondly, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men are ouercome with the pleasure of hearing tales and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, tending to adulterie and to whoredome; and to this head I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176639:26"/>the pleasure of prophane dancing, a sinne of which I haue likewise spoken: I thinke it were better for some to follow their children to punishment, then to prophane dancing, tending to whorish vice; for if they followed them to punishment, they might be brought to repentance: but in dancing they are so commended that many of them are ledde vnto hell by it. The third pleasure is the pleasure of seeing, to which may be referred the pleasure of getting riches, yea of whoredome, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men haue <hi>eies full of adultery,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> speaketh, 2. Epist 2. chap. And as whoredome may be referred to this head, so likwise may it be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the fourth plesure of touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: of which I wil say nothing: see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then pleasure is such a deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full harlot, that it deceaueth al the
<pb facs="tcp:176639:27"/>senses, let vs beware of it: <hi>vultu, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce fallit &amp; veste,</hi> She deceaueth by her voice, by her countenance, and by her garments: By her voice she deceaueth the eare, by her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the eie, by her sweete gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the sense of smelling: but some man will say, what must wee doe then, seeing pleasure is so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull, and deceaueth the senses? I answere, that wee must watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our senses; My sonne saith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> 23. of the <hi>Pro.</hi> 25. ver. <hi>Giue mee thine heart, and let thine eies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in my waies:</hi> And againe in the 4. of <hi>Prou.</hi> 23. <hi>Keepe thine heart with all diligence, for thereout com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth life;</hi> the senses are the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the minde, they are also the doores of the same, eyther to let good or bad thinges into it; Wherefore as <hi>Iob</hi> made a Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with his eies, so must men
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176639:27"/>make a couenant with their senses that they beholde no euill things: <hi>Non debent sensus, ad instar petulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ancillae foras euagari,</hi> our senses ought not to wander abroad, like vnto wanton maids; this made <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocrates</hi> to say, <hi>nihil interest pedes an oculos in aliena ponas domo,</hi> It is no matter whether thou fastenest thine eies or thy feete in another mans house: Wherefore as the Mariners leaue not the Sea, but decline the rockes of the Sea; so we must not leaue the world, but decline the wickednes of the same; and as <hi>Vlisses</hi> stopped his owne eares and his companions with waxe, that they might not heare the inchantments of the Syrens; So must wee stop our eares, yea vaile all our senses, that wee heare not the inchantments of the world: Wherefore O young men
<pb facs="tcp:176639:28"/>shut your eies, stop your eares, least you bee bewitched with the vaine pleasures of this world; can you not put a difference betwixt flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie and true friendship: pleasure is but a flattering friend, in a worde it is a deceiptfull enemie; <hi>Qui cauet ne decipiatur, vix cauet: saepe is cautor captus est:</hi> He that taketh heed least hee be deceiued is not alwaies wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie enough; for sometime hee is caught, bee hee neuer so warie. Now that men may auoide plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, I will set them downe these reasons, why they should doe so. First let the yong man remember that pleasure is short, but the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment is eternall: <hi>voluptas bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, paena aeterna. Salomon</hi> in the 7. chap. of <hi>Eccles.</hi> and 8. verse saith; <hi>that as the noise of thornes vnder a pot, so is the laughter of a foole:</hi> as the thornes crackle for a while and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176639:28"/>profit nothing, so doth pleasure: <hi>Cogitate</hi> saith <hi>Cato, si quid per labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem recte facitis, labor cito recedit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactum remanet, si quid per volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem nequiter, haec cito perit et illud numquam abibit:</hi> Consider if you haue done any thing wel bypaines the paines is quickly gone, the good worke remaineth still; but if you haue done any thing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through pleasure, the pleasure soone perisheth, but the wicked deede neuer departeth: the Iewes vse, that the new married folke, doe breake a glasse, to signifie the fragility of humane things. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the companion of pleasure is sorrow and griefe: <hi>Ita dijs placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, voluptati vt maeror comes conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatur.</hi> So it pleased God, that sorrow should follow pleasure as a companion: <hi>Quam mira res est,</hi> saith <hi>Plato in Phaede, quam homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:176639:29"/>appellant voluptatem, quamque miro modo se habet ad dolorem.</hi> What a strange thing is that which men call pleasure, and how wonderfully doth it respect griefe? He which layeth hold on pleasure, laieth hold also on griefe; so that they are knit together, as it were by one head: this might be speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by many examples, as of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, dauncing, and drunkennesse; but I forbeare them, and come to a third reason, why men should forsake their pleasures. Thirdly, there is a satietie of pleasure, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there is a satietie of al things, and therefore of pleasure: the reason of this <hi>Aristotle</hi> giueth, <hi>Ethic.</hi> 7. the last chap. because our nature is not simple, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of diuers things; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, saith he, <hi>Deus vna &amp; simplici in perpetuum voluptate perfruitur:</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:176639:29"/>God doeth enioy one simple de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light for euer, because his nature is most simple, and without compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition. If there were any man of <hi>Philoxenus</hi> his mind, who wished that he had a Cranes necke, that he might take more pleasure in his banquets; yet would there be a satietie in his delight: is there not a satiety of any pleasure which man taketh in hand, so that hee leaueth one pleasure and taketh another in hand? and this argueth that a man is sicke in his very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures: <hi>Proprium aegrotantium est nunc vnum nunc aliud velle, fastidire cibos, lectum, modo huc modo illuc impatienter se conuertere.</hi> It is the propertie ofsicke men, sometime to will this, sometimes that; to loath meate, euen the bedde also, and impatiently to turne himselfe, sometimes hither, sometimes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:176639:30"/>Fourthly, pleasures make the voluptuous men that are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted vnto them, stocks and fools: <hi>Whoredome and wine taketh away the mind,</hi> saith <hi>Hosea,</hi> chap. 4. ver. 11. and needes must they so doe, for they drie the braine much, they trouble the spirits to much; they wound the phantasie: yea, they stirre vp exceeding griefes in the desire. Hence it is, that very few addicted to these pleasures, are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto God: it is a principle in Philosophy that <hi>excellens sensibile corrumpit sensum,</hi> the obiect of the sense, being too vehement, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the sense; as it may be seene in those that dwell neare to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Nylus, whose fall depriueth them of their hearing; so the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency of pleasure depriueth men of their senses.</p>
               <p>Fiftly and lastly, there is a woe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176639:30"/>in Scripture, denounced against those that follow their pleasures: <hi>VVoe vnto them that are mightie to drinke wine, and to them that are strong to power in strong drinke.</hi> Esay 5. ver. 22. <hi>VVoe vnto them that drink wine in bowles, and annoint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with the chiefe oyntments, but no man is sory for the affliction of Ioseph.</hi> Amo. 6. ver. 6. In the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the rich man, this is alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Luke 16. ver. 25. <hi>Remember that thou in thy life time receiuedst thy pleasure, and likewise</hi> Lazarus <hi>paines: but now is he comforted, and thou art tormented:</hi> to be then in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pleasure, ease, wealth, peace, and prosperity in this world is peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and a signe of paines in the next: and here by the way men may obserue, that it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, though there bee many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes; for the Papists religion is a
<pb facs="tcp:176639:31"/>very pleasant religion to corrupt nature; there is musicke for the eares; goodly Images for the eies; yea, delights for the other senses; yea, there is pleasure for the flesh: for what care many to commit whoredome, seeing by confessing to a Priest they may haue their sins pardoned? Yea, is not this religion very pleasant to Priestes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues? who, as <hi>Aluarius</hi> writeth, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aepe cum parochianis mulieribus quas ad confessionem admittunt, sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestissime fornicantur,</hi> do oftentimes commit fornication most wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the women, that doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse their sinnes vnto them: if they say that satisfaction is enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, which is very grieuous. I answere with the Prophet <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chah,</hi> chap. 6. ver. 4. <hi>Will the Lord be pleased with thousands of Rammes or with tenne thousand riuers of Oyle:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176639:31"/>Shal I giue my first borne for my trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression, euen the fruit of my body for the sinne of my soule?</hi> Noting, that there is nothing so deare, but that Hypocrites will giue, rather then leaue their sinnes: <hi>Magnum non est sua, magnum est se relinquere.</hi> It is no great thing to leaue goods; it is a great thing to leaue himselfe.</p>
               <p>But now me thinkes I heare the young man, saying, Tush, I may follow my pleasures in my youth, and repent when I am olde. The young man is content, that God should haue the blinde, lame, and sicke sacrifice: but, saieth <hi>Malachy,</hi> chap. 1.8. <hi>Offer it vnto the Prince, will he be content with thee, or accept thy person, saieth the Lord of Hostes?</hi> But for the further abandoning of this base minde, remember these things which I shall set downe: First remember, that late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:176639:32"/>may bee iustly suspected; <hi>Nam si quis quinquaginta annis tibi insestus, cum te ad regiam dignitatem &amp;c.</hi> If a man should liue thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my fifty years, and seeing thee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to a Kingdome, should then seeke thy friendshippe, wouldest thou trust him? So is it to bee thought of those, who despising God, haue serued the diuell; and yet at the last houre will turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: it is to be thought I say, that they doe it more for feare of punishment, then for loue of the Iudge: Secondly, if thou repentest when thou art olde, it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that thy sinnes haue left thee, and that thou hast not forsaken thy sinnes: <hi>Peccata tua te dimiserunt, non tu pecca tua;</hi> thy sinnes haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thee a Diuorce, thou hast not giuen thy sinnes; which is a very fearefull estate: Thirdly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176639:32"/>that it is late then to begin to liue, when wee must die: <hi>Quam serum est tunc viuere incipere, cum desinendum est?</hi> How late is it then to take in hand a new life, when we must goe out of this life? Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is the Diuels perswasion, to giue him the present time, and God the time to come: Giue me, sayeth the Diuell, the time that now is; giue God the future time; giue me thy youth, and God thy olde age; giue me thy pleasant time, and God thy vnprofitable time: seeing this is the Diuels perswasion, that seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the destruction of thy soule, neuer yeeld to the same.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>quam stultum est inde velle ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem disponere, quo pauci perduxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt?</hi> How foolish a thing is it then to dispose of thy age, when fewe haue liued so long: many are dead we know before gray haires.
<pb facs="tcp:176639:33"/>Sixtly, <hi>Non te pudet reliquias vitae tibi reseruare, &amp; id solum tempus bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae menti destinari, quod in nullam rem conferri possit?</hi> art thou not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to reserue to thy selfe the dregges of thy life, and to appoint onely that time for repentance, which can be bestowed vpon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? <hi>vt ex amphora primum quod est sincerissimum fluit, grauissimum quodque &amp; turbidum subsidet: sic in ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatequod est optimum, prius est,</hi> as out of a vessell the purest liquor run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth first out, the filthy remaineth in the bottome, so in our life that which is best, is first. Seauenthly, remember that it is a hard thing to leaue custome in sinne, custome is another nature as it were, and therefore will hardly be forsaken. Eightly, remember that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is the gift of God, and his giftes are not at thy commaund.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176639:33"/>Ninthly, remember the tyrannie of death, yea the paine which thy sicknesse may bring, it may be will hardly suffer thee to thinke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; how darest thou then deferre repentance. Tenthly, the sinnes of thy youth should bee most grieuous vnto thee; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 25. Psalme, 7. verse, prayeth thus: <hi>Remember not the sinnes of my youth nor my rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but according to thy kindnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou mee, for thy goodnesse sake O Lord:</hi> These reasons may suffice to make any young man to abhorre to delay repentance; but some will say, will you depriue a man of all pleasures? God forbid, but in thy pleasures remember these rules. First measure thy pleasures by the end, if they tend to nourish sinne they are naught; hence iudge of dancing of men
<pb facs="tcp:176639:34"/>and women together which nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth whoredome; if <hi>Plato</hi> would haue euery Poet to be cast out of a commonwealth, how much more should this kinde of dancing be banished the common wealth? Secondly, hereby iudge of plaies which yeeld the very seeds of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse, <hi>Histrionici gestus,</hi> saieth <hi>Lactantius Epit. diui Insti, quibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fames foeminas imitantur, libidines quas saltando exprimunt, docent.</hi> The behauiour of plaiers wherby they doe imitate infamous women, do teach lust which they do expresse by dauncing. Secondly, measure thy pleasures by time, see thou v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest them not out of time. Blessed art thou O land, when thy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces eate in time for strength, and not for drunkennes, saith <hi>Solomon. Eccles.</hi> 10. chap. Thirdly, see that thy pleasures for the matter bee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176639:34"/>lawfull. <hi>Aristotle,</hi> 4. <hi>Ethic.</hi> 1. num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth the dicer among illiberall persons, and saith, hee is giuen to filthy gaine. <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Zenophon</hi> in his first booke of Re. saith, that dicers are idle persons: let dicers therefore looke that the matter of their play bee lawfull. Fourthly, measure thy pleasures by thy abilitie, and see that they bring thee not vnto pouertie; this hath hunting and hauking done to many. Fiftly, see that thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures bee recreations, not vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. chap. 6. verse, saith <hi>that the widdow that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in pleasure, is dead while shee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,</hi> so say I of those that liue in pleasures, and make recreations their vocations. <hi>Seneca</hi> 55. Epistle saith of an idle person, that hee is dead, the same may bee said of him that maketh pleasure his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.
<pb facs="tcp:176639:35"/>Sixtly, see that thy pleasure make thee more fit to serue God, For <hi>voluptates illae solum verae haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quae actionem pii perficiunt:</hi> those are onely true pleasures, which perfect the actions of godly men. Seuenthly, in thy pleasures begin with praier, that God may blesse them vnto thee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> saith <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> it is the best order that can bee, to begin in God and to end in God. Eightly, in all thy pleasures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the day of Iudgement, know that God will call thee to iudgement: But yet further some will say the life of a Christian is without pleasure, therefore who can endure it? O foole, deceiue not thy soule, the life of a Christian is the most pleasant life that can be, for spirituall delights are farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then bodily delightes, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176639:35"/>are many. First, man is more delighted in that he vnderstandeth things, then in that hee perceiueth them by sense; because it is a more excellent knowledge. Secondly, the knowledge of the vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is more beloued then the knowledge of the senses, for there is no man that had not rather want his bodily sight, then his sight of his soule, which is his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. Thirdly, the spirituall good which causeth ioy, is greater then any bodily good: men wil ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine from many bodily pleasures, that they mayobtaine honour: but some will say how commeth it then to passe, that bodily plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures are more followed after? There are diuers causes. First bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleasures are better knowne. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they are preseruatiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst griefes of the bodie, which
<pb facs="tcp:176639:36"/>man cannot endure, <hi>vt quidam morbo aliquo &amp; sensus stupore sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem cibi non sentiunt, sic libidino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si, auari facinorosi &amp;c.</hi> As they which are sicke feele not the sweetnes of meate, so they that are giuen to lust, to couetousnes and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes, feele not the sweetnes of true pleasure: <hi>I haue had,</hi> saith <hi>Dauid</hi> 119. Psalme, <hi>a great delight in the way of thy testimonies, as in all manner of riches:</hi> And againe, <hi>except thy lawe had beene my delight I should haue perished in mine afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> and thus much touching the first part of my text. Now I come to the second: which is a bridle and restrainte to keepe the young man from his pleasures: but know saith <hi>Solomon</hi> that God wil bring thee to iudgement for all these things: In which words I will handle three thinges. First what
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176639:36"/>Iudgement is; Secondly, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie of iudgements, Thirdly, the vse of the doctrine. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the first to omitt the diuerse significations of the worde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Iudgement is an act of a Iudge, either absoluing or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning any person: this to bee true, no man can denie, Christ is the iudge of the quicke and the dead, and hee will either absolue them, or condemne them: Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue them hee will if they bee members of his mysticall bodie; condemne them he will, if they liue in their sinnes without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; touching the diuersities of iudgements, there are two iudgments, the one particular: the other generall: The particular iudgement euery man hath at his death: the generall iudgement, shall be at Christ his second com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.
<pb facs="tcp:176639:37"/>For the proofe of this particular iudgement, it is euident that the wicked are carried to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall punishment, 16. of <hi>Luke</hi> and the godlie to eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: but it is no way probable, that the rewards should be rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before iudgement: therefore at the houre of death there is a particular iudgement. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> in his 37. Homilie vpon <hi>Mathew</hi> doeth make this plaine; <hi>Postquam,</hi> saith he, <hi>Diem tuum obieris, iudicium &amp; paena consequetur:</hi> After thou art dead, iudgement and punishment will follow: In which place, hee confuteth those, that thinke that Christ will bring the dead to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: he vseth this argument; after death there followeth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and after iudgement punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; therefore there is no place for repentance. By the way wee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176639:37"/>may obserue, what is become of Popish Purgatorie, wherefore wee must hold with <hi>Augustine, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De Origi. Animae. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Illu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rectissime &amp; valde saiubriter credit, iudicari a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimas cum de corporibus exierint, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam veniant ad illud iudicium, quo cas oportet iam redditis corporibus iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicari.</hi> He doth very well beleeue, that the soules are iudged when they goe out of their bodies, before they come to that iudgement, in which they shall bee iudged with their bodies. But some will say, Then to what end serueth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall iudgement? I answere, there are many causes of the same: First, that the mercy and iustice of God might be made manifest, God hath made all things to declare his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the wicked might accuse him of iniustice, therefore he will haue the same made manifest to the
<pb facs="tcp:176639:38"/>whole world, as likewise his mercy in the saluation of his seruants.</p>
               <p>Secondly, God will haue his son Christ Iesus, publikely to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and honoured: He was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely dishonoured in this world, therefore his father will haue him publikely honoured at the day of iudgement.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Lord will haue his seruants publikely honoured: the Saints haue been made a spectacle to men in this world, therefore he will haue them honoured before the whole world. Fourthly, whole man must bee iudged and receiue his reward, both in soule and in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; therefore there must be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall day of iudgement. Fiftly, the workes of men are not ended at their death: the wicked men by their examples, writings, and many euill deedes, doe much hurt, euen
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176639:38"/>after their death: and the godly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their death, doe much good by writings; therfore when there shal be an end of good and euill works, which shall bee at the end of the world, then shall be a generall day of iudgement: And that there shal be a iudgement, it is plaine by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reasons: First, many wicked men escape vnpunished in this life, therefore seeing the Lord is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he must needes punish them in the life to come: wherefore excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently speaketh <hi>Isocrates</hi> in his <hi>Parae. Iusti, si nulla alia re iniustis praestant, spe certe bona sunt superiores.</hi> If the iust excell the vniust in nothing, yet are they better in respect of hope: Secondly, the conscience of a man doth declare euidently, that there shall be a iudgement, for that will accuse him most fearefully, after sinne, which is a liuely representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:176639:39"/>of a iudgement to come: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conscience is called, before sinne be committed, a bridle; and after sinne, a scourge or whippe. To giue one or two examples: <hi>Pausanias</hi> after he had rauished <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onice,</hi> how fearefully was he troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? Her shape did appeare vnto him in his sleepe, and threatned pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, saying, <hi>paena tibi luenda est</hi> thou must be punished. <hi>Nero</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing murdred his mother, as <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> writeth <hi>Saepe confessus est se exagitari materna specie,</hi> oftentimes acknowledged, that hee was tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with her shape: Thirdly, there are iudgments in this world; therefore there is a Iudge of the world: God hath fearefully puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed many sinners, as swearers, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, vsurers, euen in this life; which is an euident argument, that there is a iudge of the world. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176639:39"/>writeth <hi>Augustine</hi> in his 1. booke <hi>De ciuit. Dei,</hi> chap. 3. If God should punish no sinne in this life, his prouidence would not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued: if he should punish al sinne, nothing would be thought to bee reserued to the day of iudgement. Fourthly, it is an article of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, that Christ shall come to iudge the quick and the dead: Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Sibill</hi> hath prophesied of Christ his second comming to iudgment, writing thus: <hi>Tunc castus Christus ponet certamina iusta, ornabitque pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bos aeternaque praemia reddet.</hi> Then chast Christ shall compound all controuersies: hee shall beautifie the good, and giue them euerlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rewards. Now I come to the vses of this doctrine, which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: first, it should make the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters diligent in preaching; <hi>I charge thee before God,</hi> saieth Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2.
<pb facs="tcp:176639:40"/>Tim. chap. 4. ver. 12. <hi>and before Iesus Christ, who shall come to iudge the quicke and the dead, that thou preach the word, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, it should teach Magistrates to iudge righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgement, for they haue a Iudge in heauen: Thirdly, it should teach men to be fruitfull in good workes: for although workes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue nothing, yet shall men be iudged according to works, because they doe declare a man to bee in Christ Iesus. Fourthly, it teacheth men to abstaine from all vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iudgements, for God is our Iudge: Fiftly, it teacheth men, little to esteeme these vnchristian cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, that men will giue one of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: Sixtly, it teacheth all men to haue a cleare conscience; for if our conscience doe condemne vs, God is greater then our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Seuenthly, it should stay
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176639:40"/>mens mindes from the greedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of this world: Lastly, it should teach young men to absteine from the vnlawfull pleasures of this life, Know that God will bring thee to iudgement, whosoeuer thou art that art addicted to thy pleasures. <hi>Sed quam caecus inest vitiis amor? Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne futurum, despicitur, suadentque &amp;c.</hi> But alas, how blinde is the loue of vice? all things to come are despised; things present perswade, profite and pleasure, neglecting punishment, causeth men to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, while that punishment is deferred. Thus much shall serue to haue spoken of this text: the Lord of his infinite goodnesse and mercy grant, that in al our thoghts, wordes, and deedes, wee haue the day of iudgement before our eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:176639:41"/>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:176639:41"/>
               <head>THE DIFFICVLTIE of Saluation.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>MAT. 19.25.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Who then can be saued?</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Iesus Christ imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly before these wordes, had taught this doctrine: that rich men are hardly saued, which he made manifest by apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbiall speech: <hi>It is harder for a
<pb facs="tcp:176639:42"/>Camell to goe thorow the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of heauen;</hi> vpon which doctrine and prouerbe, the Disciples inferre this question: <hi>Who then can be saued?</hi> as if they had said, then is saluation indeede a difficult matter; for rich men haue the most especiall meanes to be saued: they haue wealth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may get knowledge; but, as <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, Prouerbes 17. ver. 16. <hi>Wherefore is there a prize in the hand of a foole to get wisedome, and he hath no heart?</hi> Againe, they haue whereof to releeue the poore; so that they make them friends of the vnrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> Luke 16. ver. 9, <hi>Make you friends,</hi> saith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Christ, <hi>with the riches of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, that when yee shall want, they may receiue you into euerlasting habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations:</hi> Furthermore, they haue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176639:42"/>leisure to pray and instruct their families, but they haue no care of these dueties. For the further explaining of the words; the word <hi>Who</hi> is sometime a word of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as Gal. the 5. ver. 7. <hi>Ye did run well, who letted you, that yee did not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the truth: Non interrogantis est illud quis, sed deplorātis,</hi> saith <hi>Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> that Who is not a word of as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, but a word of bewailing. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, this word Who is a word of exhortation, Hos. 14. ver. 10. <hi>Who is wise, that he may vnderstand these things?</hi> so likewise in the 107. Psalme, <hi>Who is wise, that he may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue these things?</hi> and Ier. 9. ver. 11. <hi>Who is wise, that he may vnderstand this?</hi> Thirdly, this word Who is a word of wondering, Esay 53. ver 1. <hi>VVho hath beleeued our report!</hi> Fourthly, it is a word of questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and so it is in this place: <hi>VVho
<pb facs="tcp:176639:43"/>then can be saued?</hi> Now concerning the word <hi>Saued:</hi> sometimes by sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is ment temporall saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that is preseruation: 1. of Tim. 4.10. God is said to be <hi>the Sauiour of all men, especially of those that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,</hi> that is the preseruer. Psalme 36. ver. 6. <hi>Thou Lord dost saue man and beast:</hi> that is, thou preseruest them. But in this place it noteth not preseruation, but eternall sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as in many other places of holy scripture; the words then doe not deny saluation to rich men, but note the difficultie of saluation. Here two errors are to be auoided, the first is we must not thinke that riches are vnlawfull for christians: the holy Scriptures do euery where forbid thefts, and commend almes; which would neuer haue bin done, if riches had bene vnlawfull for Christians: The second errour is,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176639:43"/>wee must not thinke that almes is sufficient vnto saluation, without saith, hope, loue, repentance, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces of God: for, saith our Sauiour Christ, Luke 13. <hi>Except ye repent, ye shall all likewise perish:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1. Cor. 13. saith, <hi>If I feede the poore with al my goods, and though I giue my bodie to be burned, and haue not loue, it profiteth nothing.</hi> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in his 21. booke <hi>De ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Dei,</hi> 22. writeth thus: <hi>qui fecerit (inquit) elemosynas, quamuis mores in melius non mutauerit, sed inter ipsas suas elemosynas, &amp;c.</hi> There are some that hold, that hee which giueth almes, although hee mendeth not his life, but liueth wickedly; yet shall he haue iudgement with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: so that he shall neuer be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, or els he shall be deliuered out of damnation, eyther after some short or long time. This is
<pb facs="tcp:176639:44"/>a damnable opinion, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euery where requireth vnto saluation, a change of our liues; yet should it seeme, that some are possessed with it, euen in these daies, for there are fearefull cursers, vsurers, and such as liue in other sinnes; yet because they giue now and then almes to the poore, they expect and looke for saluation: these two errours being avoided, now I come to the handling of the text. The doctrine which ariseth from thence is this: namely, that it is an exceeding hard matter for a man to be saued: yea, indeede it is a wonder that any man attaineth vnto saluation: to make this point plaine, is it not a great worke to make something of nothing? If thou wilt be saued, God must work as great a worke for thee, for thou must be a new creature, 2. Cor. 5.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176639:44"/>ver. 17. <hi>If any man be in Christ Iesus, let him be a new creature:</hi> so Gal. 6.15. saith Saint <hi>Paul, for in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, neither circumcision auaileth any thing, nor vncircumcision, but a new creature.</hi> Againe, Ephes. 2.10. <hi>for we are his workemanshippe, created in Christ Iesus, vnto good workes:</hi> so then is it as great a matter for any to be saued, as to be created? Yea, in some sort greater; for when God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the world, he found nothing to resist his will, but in this new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, he findeth the peruerse will of man, to resist his will; which peruersenes he must take away. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, men are dead in their sins by nature, Ephes. 2.7. Is it not a wonderfull worke to raise a dead man, and to giue him life? Euen so is it to raise a man out of the graue of his sinnes, and to giue him a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life. Excellently therefore
<pb facs="tcp:176639:45"/>doeth <hi>Aquinas</hi> hold <hi>prima secundae 113. quae. Ar. 9.</hi> that <hi>iustificatio impij est maximum opus Dei.</hi> To make an vngodly man righteous is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test worke of God. <hi>Iudicet qu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test,</hi> saith <hi>Augustine, Trac.</hi> 72. in Ioh. <hi>vtrum maius sit iustos Angelos creare, quam impios iustificare, certe si aequalis est vtrumque potentiae, hoc maioris est misericordiae.</hi> Let him iudge that is able, whether it is a greater matter to create the Angels righteous, or to iustifie the vngodly man; that is, to make him righteous: verily if both be of equall power, yet is it a worke of greater mercy, to make an vnrighteous man righteous. To come to particulars, it is a harder matter for a rich man to be saued: First, in respect of pride, for he is in danger to be proude, 1. Tim. 6.17. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high minded.</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:176639:45"/>The Prophet <hi>Hos.</hi> chap. 13. verse 6. saith of the Israelites, that <hi>they were filled, and their heart was exalted.</hi> I know, saieth <hi>Cato</hi> in <hi>Gell.</hi> in his 7. booke and 3. chapter, that most men by prosperity do waxe proud; but this should not be, for <hi>quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum arboris ramus quo est plenior, eo est grauior:</hi> euen as the bow of a tree, the fuller of fruit it is, the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it is: so the more blessings the Lorde doe bestow vpon men, the more humble they should be. <hi>Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colae</hi> saith <hi>Plutarch, libenter vident spicas quae vergunt ad terram, quae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ob leuitatem sursum attolluntur, inanes sunt.</hi> Husbandmen doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly behold eares of corne that turne towards the earth; for they which looke vpward are emptie, and haue nothing in them: so may I say, God regardeth the humble, but the proud he scorneth. Seeing
<pb facs="tcp:176639:46"/>then rich men bee in danger of pride, and they which will be saued must be humble, it must needes be, that it is a hard matter for rich men to be saued. <hi>Esto,</hi> saith <hi>Chrysostome</hi> in his Homily <hi>Profec. Euangelij. mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumaedifices, habeas elemosynas, preces, ieiunia, virtutsque omnes, humilitate non praeiecta, frustra &amp; in vanum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt omnia, facileque ruet super are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam extructum aedificium.</hi> Be it thou buildest much, thou mayest haue almes, prayers, fastings, al ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; yet if humilitie be not laide for a foundation, all is in vaine, and thy building will easily fall, beeing but vpon the sand. Secondly, it is hard for rich men to be saued, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of putting their trust in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: <hi>Charge rich men,</hi> saieth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the place before cited, <hi>that they trust not in vncertaine riches.</hi> For this cause Ephes. 5. ver. 5. a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176639:46"/>man is called an Idolater, because he putteth his trust in his riches; not onely because in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of riches, he neglecteth the seruice of God, but because he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that his life doeth consist in riches; therefore I say, is he called an Idolater. Riches through the corruption of men, do marueilous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly steale their hearts from God, for they will no longer trust God, then they see him in their Barnes or Chests. <hi>Giue me not,</hi> saith <hi>Agur</hi> 30. of the Prouerbs, 8. verse, <hi>pouertie nor riches, feede me with foode conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for me, least I be full, and denie thee, and say, VVho is the Lorde?</hi> meaning, that many rich men put their trust in their riches, and so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie God. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. To make many Gods, is no better then a kind of Atheisme: seeing then the rich man doth make many Gods, he
<pb facs="tcp:176639:47"/>is in danger to denie God; and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is in danger of both these: to make both many Gods, and to denie God, it must needes bee a hard matter for him to be saued. Thirdly, it is a hard matter for a rich man to be saued in respect of couetousnes: the more riches doe encrease, the more they are desired. The desire of riches is like vnto a dropsie, <hi>crescit indulgens sibi dirus hydrops;</hi> the more he that hath the dropsie drinketh, the more he desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; so the more riches that a rich man hath, the more he desireth: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch that physick doth encrease the disease. Thirst is quenched with drinke, hunger with meate, but the thirst and hunger of riches is neuer satisfied. Excellent therefore is the speech of the holy Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 62. Psalme, <hi>If riches encrease, set not your hearts vpon them. There
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176639:47"/>be three things that will not be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> saith <hi>Agur,</hi> Pro. 30.15. <hi>yea, foure that say not, it is enough: the graue, the barren wombe, the earth that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be satisfied with water, and the fire that saith not, It is enough.</hi> The same may be said of couetousnes, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer satisfied: <hi>qui plus cupiunt, sic di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitias habent, quomodo habere dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur febrem: diceredebemus, febris il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumtenet; sic Diuitiae illum possident, non ille Diuitias.</hi> They that desire more, possesse riches as a man is said to haue an ague; we should say the ague hath him: so riches pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse him, not he riches: wherefore Christian brother, whosoeuer thou art, learne to moderate thy appetite, concerning riches; <hi>for they that will be rich,</hi> saith the Apostle, 1. Tim. 6.9. <hi>fall into temptation and snares, and into many foolish and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some lusts, which drowne men in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb facs="tcp:176639:48"/>and destruction.</hi> A poore man needeth many things, a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man all things. As men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vse a horse without a bridle, no more can a man vse riches without moderation of his appetite: the best riches then are want of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of riches. Fourthly, rich men are hardly saued in respect of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, for many of them, are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly addicted vnto a voluptuous life, and indeede liue in no calling; onely pleasure is their calling, as if God had euer ordained any such calling: <hi>They take the Tabret and the Harpe and reioyce in the sound of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. Iob</hi> 21.12. I take not away pleasures from men, but I desire to temper them with an holy and Christian vocation. If the heathen man said, that <hi>qui ad eruditionem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirant, iis omittendae sunt omnes voluptates, relinquenda studia delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationis,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176639:48"/>ioci conuiuium, sermo etiam pene omium familiarium deserendus.</hi> They which aspire to learning, must abandon pleasures, relinquish delights, and forsake mirth, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting; yea, the talke almost of familiar friends: how much more may I say, that they which will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to the Kingdome of heauen, must abandon their delights and pleasures. Let no man thinke that God hath placed them in this world, to be the seruants of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, but that they should follow after vertue: many men desire to be accounted valiant; here is valor and strength to be shewed: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in vanquishing their pleasure: <hi>Haniball</hi> when he was nine yeares olde, sware that he would be an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the very name of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: we in baptisme vowed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquish pleasures, yet doe not men
<pb facs="tcp:176639:49"/>forsake the same: If <hi>Euripides,</hi> as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth, findeth fault with those that vsed musicke at their banquets, because it is to bee vsed for comfort and solace, and not to weaken mens minds with pleasure: how much more may they iustly be found fault withall, that vse nothing els but pleasures and pastimes? Hence is it that they are so nice, that they can beare no afflictions. Excellent is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of <hi>Isocrates:</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Exercisethy selfe in voluntarie labours, that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est beare necessary afflictions: but enough of this point. Fiftly, rich men are hardly saued in respect of cruelty: for many of them are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell oppressors. To this head I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre Inclosers, who turne men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to sheepe; so that they dispeople
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176639:49"/>townes, and disteeple Churches. I cannot more fitly resemble these men, then to <hi>Aesops</hi> Lyon, who said, one part is mine, because I am most worthy, another is mine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I am strongest, the third is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so mine, because I laboured most, and if you will not also graunt mee the fourth part, and indeed all, fare-well friendshippe: so saith the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closer, one part is mine, I am most worthy, for I am a Gentleman; an other part is mine, I am strongest, for I am wealthiest, the third part is mine, for I paid for all, and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fourth part, except thou wilt also graunt me that, fare-well friendshippe. If the eloquent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Esay</hi> in his 5. chap. and 8. verse, denounced a <hi>woe vnto th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se that ioyne house to house, and lay fielde to fielde, till there bee no place, that they may be placed themselues in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest
<pb facs="tcp:176639:50"/>of the earth.</hi> Why should not a woe be denounced against those that ioyne fielde to fielde, so that there bee no Commons for the poore, nor corne and graine for them: haue not those Inclosers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the law of nature, which is, to doe as men would be done vnto? Would they be thus dealt withall themselues? I pray God that these Inclosers inclose not the Diuell in their Pastures, and their soules in hell. Againe, to the head of crueltie I referre vsurie: the vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer may be fitly resembled to light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which melteth the monie in the purse, and neuer hurteth the purse. <hi>Loculis integris,</hi> (saith <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca) pecunia, quae in his fuerat, confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta reperitur: quia ignis tenu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per occulta foramina transit.</hi> The Lord in the 23. of Deut. ve. 19. saith plainely, <hi>Thou shalt not giue to vsury
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176639:50"/>to thy brother, as vsury of money, vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of meate, vsury of any thing, that i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> put to vsury.</hi> Hence I thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; to no brother must we lend vpon vsury, but all Christians are brethren: <hi>Ergo,</hi> to no Christian must we lend vpon vsury. If it be obiected, that the Iewes were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to lend to strangers; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere with <hi>Ambrose, Cui iure infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur ar ma, huic legitime indicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vsurae:</hi> they that might lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be killed, might lawfully be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed with vsury; and in very deed the practise of the Iewes doth manifest this permission in some sort, for one Iew will not lend to another vpon vsury; if he doth, he is condemned by the law of God; and shall one Christian then lend to another vpon vsury? My pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose is not to handle this same at large, therefore I leaue the vsurer
<pb facs="tcp:176639:51"/>condemned by Gods law, by mans law, by the law of nature, and by his owne conscience, and say with <hi>Plautus, Quid est danista? genus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum improbissimum est.</hi> What is an vsurer? It is a most wicked kind of men, for indeed he is worse then a Iew; for one Iew will not take vsury of another, but the vsurer wil take vsury of his Christian brother: hee is worse then death, for death killeth but the bodie, but the vsurer killeth both bodie and soule. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to this head of cruelty, I referre oppressing Land-lordes, who, as <hi>Galba</hi> made his Citizens most drie sponges, so these men make their tennants: their rents are now set vpon the tenter-hookes, and they grind the faces of the poore, not considering that they are the Lords tennants: and lastly, not thinking vpon the saying of <hi>Iulius Caesar,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176639:51"/>misera comes senectutis, est pristinae crudelitatis memoria.</hi> The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of olde crueltie, is a misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companion of olde age. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> being asked where hee had his tresures, answered at his friends: so cannot those raking Land-lords say, for few friends haue they: this is a crying sinne, and day and night it maketh such a noyse in the eares of the Lord, that he will not heare the prayers of those oppressing Land-lords. The Land-lord now a dayes letteth his grounds best, that destroyeth his tennants: if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man marueile at these thinges, let him remember, that old age in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth to couetousnes. <hi>Hoc viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um affert senectus hominibus, attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores sunt omnes ad rem, quam sat est:</hi> This is the fault of olde age, it is too much giuen to the worlde; no maruell then, though men bee
<pb facs="tcp:176639:52"/>exceedingly addicted to this sinne. Sixtly, rich men are hardly saued, in this respect, that they are impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of reproofe, which is a meanes to saue mens soules. The rich man thinketh that he must not be reproued, for hee is a certaine God vpon the earth: <hi>Diues quasi Deus.</hi> If a Minister now a daies crie <hi>vae vobis,</hi> Woe vnto you rich men: it will be hard, if they bring him not <hi>coram nobis,</hi> before the Magistrate. <hi>Minucius,</hi> as <hi>Liuie</hi> reporteth, sayde <hi>eum esse primum virum, qui recte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulit; eum secundum, qui bene monen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti obtemperat: qui nec bene monet nec paret, extremi ingenij esse,</hi> that hee was the best man, that could giue good counsaile; he was the second that did obey, but he that did ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giue good counsell nor obey, was of a nature to bee deplored. What nature then haue these rich
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176639:52"/>men, that will neither giue good counsell nor take good counsell? Take none they will not, for they cannot abide to bee reproued: reprouing is rayling in their corrupt iudgement. But let them knowe, that <hi>Isocrates</hi> the Heathen man could put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt these two. <hi>Nam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusare putandi sunt</hi> (saith he) <hi>qui lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi causa conuicia dicunt; admone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, qui propter audientium vtilitatem, idem faciunt.</hi> They are said to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse that tell men of their faults to hurt them, but they doe admonish that tel men of their faults, for their good: seeing then that rich men are tolde of their faults for their good, and not for their hurt, let them put a difference betwixt rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and reproofe.</p>
               <p>But howsoeuer these men are impatient of reproofe, let the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister
<pb facs="tcp:176639:53"/>do his duety; let him not be <hi>Lapis laeuigatorius,</hi> a sleeke-stone to soothe and smoothe men in their sinnes. Woe vnto them that call euill good, and good euill: sinne is sinne in whomsoeuer it is found, whether he be rich or poore, God respecteth no mans person: let the rich man then as he deserueth, haue his reproofe. Seuenthly and lastly, a rich man is hardly saued, for he is in danger to breake all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God, or the most of them: he is in danger of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, as I shewed before: yea, is he not in danger of swearing? And doe not rich men now a daies cracke oathes, as the bird <hi>Sitta</hi> cracketh nuts? Doeth not the rich man most wofully prophane the Sabboth, in vsing faires and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly busines vpon the same? Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, he is disobedient to his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176639:53"/>for he careth not for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Gods word, who should be his fathers: yea, hee careth not to murther by not feeding the poore: and what careth hee to commit whoredome, because by his wealth he can countenance his sinne? Stealings, false witnesse, and coueting are his daily sinnes. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then that these things are thus; how hard is it for a rich man to be saued? But some man will say, is it not also hard for a poore man to be saued? Yes very hard: for when our Sauiour Christ saith, <hi>It is hard for a rich man to be saued,</hi> hee doeth not denie, but that it is also hard for a poore man to be saued. The affirming of the one, doeth not make a deniall of the other; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it is also exceeding hard for a poore man to bee saued: First, a poore man is in danger of impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie
<pb facs="tcp:176639:54"/>in respect of his pouertie. How doe the poore fret and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure against God, because they are in want? Secondly, it is a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter also for a poore man to be saued in respect of enuie, for the poore men enuie the estate of rich men, and pine away with sorrow, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are in better estate then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: this is a very fearefull sinne, for they should reioice at the good one of another, as members of the same Mysticall bodie. <hi>The poore and the rich meete together</hi> (saith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> Pro. 22.2.) <hi>the Lord is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of them all.</hi> Againe, <hi>inuidia ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa maximam partem veneni sui bibit.</hi> Enuy drinketh the greatest part of his owne poyson. The Serpents keepe poyson without their owne hurt, and powre it out to the hurt of others; but the enuious man keepeth his enuie, which is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176639:54"/>poyson, to his own hurt, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it out to the hurt of others, and to the ruine of his owne soule. Thirdly, it is hard for a poore man to be saued, in respect of lying, for because hee is poore, hee thinketh that he may lye to releeue himselfe. Fourthly, it is hard for a poore man to be saued, in respect of steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for to helpe himselfe, he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to commit this sinne. <hi>Giue me not pouerty</hi> (saith <hi>Agur,</hi> Prou. 30.8.) <hi>least I be poore and steale, and take the name of God in vaine.</hi> Now let not any man take me thus, as if rich men would not murmure, as if they were not enuious, or would not steale; or as if poore men might not be proude, couetous, or cruell: but as it is said in the 25. of Ecclesiasticus, ver. 2. <hi>Three sorts of men my soule hateth, and I vtterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the life of them: a poore man
<pb facs="tcp:176639:55"/>that is proud: a rich man that is a lyar, and an old adulterer that doteth:</hi> So then it is monstrous for rich men to lye, as it is for poore men to be proude.</p>
               <p>Furthermore I might shew that it is a hard matter for them both to be saued: I meane both poore and rich, in respect of buying and sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; <hi>for as a naile in the wall, sticketh fast betweene the ioynts of stones, so doth sinne sticke betweene buying and selling,</hi> Eccles. 27.2. But I come to the vses of the doctrine: The first vse of the doctrine is this: namely, that men ascribe their saluation to God alone, not partly to him and partly to themselues, seeing salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is as great a worke as creation. Excellently writeth <hi>Bernard</hi> in his booke of free-will, <hi>Id totum gratia Dei est, quod creamur sanamur, &amp; sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uamur.</hi> It is the meere grace of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176639:55"/>God that wee are created, that we are made whole, and that wee are saued. Againe, saith <hi>Augustine</hi> in his sentences, <hi>Ad caelestis Hierusalem consortium non ascendit, nisi qui toto corde profitetur, non proprij esse operis, sed diuini muneris, quod ascendit.</hi> He ascendeth not to heauen, who doth not acknowledge with his whole heart, that it is not by his owne worke, but by Gods gift, that he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth thither. Furthermore, saith the same <hi>Augustine, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De peccatorum meritis &amp; remissione cap.</hi> 18. <hi>laborant homines inuenire, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra voluntate quid boni sit nostrum, quod nobis non sit ex Deo; &amp; quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do inueniri possit ignoro.</hi> Men doe labor to find in our wil, what good is ours, which is not of God; but how it should bee found I know not. Lastly, in his 106. Epistle he writeth sweetly; <hi>gratia Deisic ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur,
<pb facs="tcp:176639:56"/>vt nec voluntas accipientium praetermittatur vel adiungatur, sed subsequatur; quandoquidem tantum beneficium non solum non libentibus sed etiam reluctantibus datur.</hi> Gods grace doth so worke, that neither the will of him that receiueth it, is past ouer or ioyned with the same grace, but followeth it, seeing so great a benefite is not only giuen to those that are not willing, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to those that resist the same. The second vse of the doctrine is this; seeing it is so hard a matter to be saued, let men take paines in this busines of saluation: hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters must be laboured: wonderfull it is to see what paines men take in the things of this life, but most piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to behold what little paines they take in the busines of saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if it were a matter of no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Thirdly, seeing it is so hard
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176639:56"/>a matter, both for rich and poore to be saued; let them eschue the sinnes that hinder their saluation: let the rich man eschue pride, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, couetousnes and voluptu ous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: let the poore man eschue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, enuie, lying and stealing. Lastly, seeing it is so hard a matter to attaine vnto saluation, what thankefulnesse ought they to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to GOD, who hath wrought this great worke of saluation in them: <hi>laudabo deum ob beneficium creationis: sed magnificabo &amp; extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam eum ob beneficium redemptionis.</hi> I will praise God for the benefite of creation; but I wil magnifie and extoll him for the benefite of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demption. It cost him the blood of his owne Sonne to saue men, so did it not in the worke of mans creation. The Lorde of his infinite and great mercy worke
<pb facs="tcp:176639:57"/>this great worke of saluation both in rich and poore, both in high and low: if this be not wrought in them, it had bin good for them they had neuer beene borne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>